# Luiz Gonzaga dos Santos Filho, MBA

🕈 Vancouver, Canada 🛽 🛖 www.luiz.dev 🔝 Email 🛗 LinkedIn 🧐 Topmate 🛂 SpeakerDeck 🕠 GitHub

A brazillian-canadian people-first leader building impactful products and high-performing teams for ~21.5 years.

I grow people with empathy, trust and accountability and organizations of all sizes with efficient and low-touch processes.

I'm continually upskilling myself and love sharing what I know. Feel free to check some of my testimonials and recommendations on my LinkedIn and Topmate profiles.

For a more verbose version of my resumé, visit luiz.dev/cv/verbose.

# **Experience**

# Software Engineering Manager → Senior Software Engineering Manager @ Coursera

Feb 2021 – present

- Drove Enterprise growth: led key Enterprise initiatives and products, unlocking double digits of millions of dollars in recurring revenue
- Grew the Enterprise org: managed several teams and charters, hired and promoted engineers to Senior, Staff and Manager
- Enhanced organizational efficiency: conceptualized, implemented and improved several team and org-wide processes, resulting in improved metrics and accountability, reduced touchpoints and better-informed leadership decision-making
- Championed DE&I and well-being: authored and drove different org-wide policies around DE&I, measurably increased our hiring pipeline's diversity and maintained highest team retention in the org

# Software Engineering Manager II → Software Engineering Manager III @ Amazon / AWS

(Sep 2017 - Dec 2020

- At Amazon Payments: led a cross-functional team to deliver the end-to-end payments integration for Amazon Turkey (amazon.com.tr), involving international and cross-department collaboration and materializing Amazon's expansion in Europe; drove early adoption of PSD2 regulations, ensuring European market compliance ahead of competitors; owned Payment on Delivery for India market
- At AWS Route53: hired and grew a team from scratch; measurably improved operational efficiency, accessibility, and usability across five different products; owned multiple product roadmaps and delivered two global product launches, expanding AWS Route53's presence into new markets and regions
- Drove organizational change and fostered inclusion: improved our sourcing efficiency by ~32% and our pipeline's diversity by ~11%; championed an engineering-wide policy to promote inclusion and belonging; as a certified Cultural Competences for Teams instructor, trained hundreds of leaders and engineers around diversity and inclusion
- Mentored and supported other managers: served on the Software Engineering Manager Peer Advisory board, providing guidance and support to peers

# Senior Frontend Engineer → Frontend Team Lead @ Brandwatch

Apr 2016 – Feb 2017

- As the Frontend team lead: helped the PM with agile ceremonies and backlog prioritization; liaison with the team manager in the UK headquarters
- As a Senior Frontend Engineer: worked existing and new feature development on Brandwatch's main product (Analytics); refactored thousands of files on a 5-year-old jQuery codebase, improving bundle size, patching security vulnerabilities, and enabling new features to be used

#### Full-stack engineer @ X-Team

Apr 2015 – Apr 2015

 Short collaboration with X-Team's CTO researching, planning and developing the next phase of X-Labs (their open source initiative) and other internal projects involving IndexedDB

#### Software Engineering Manager @ DataEasy

( Jun 2014 – Mar 2016

- Led Engineering Transformation: directed a company-wide shift to modern DevOps and ChatOps practices, including Git, SemVer, CI pipelines, live application monitoring, automated release management, enabling higher quality and faster releases and allowing the IT department to stay leaner
- Championed Process Improvement: mapped all engineering processes, reduced touchpoints and staffing needs
- Fostered growth and upskilling: partnered with a local university to provide automated testing courses for senior engineers, streamlining testing cycles and reducing release bottlenecks
- Cultivated Innovation and Learning: created a bi-weekly program fostering innovation and knowledge sharing through tech talks and experimentation with new technologies

#### Senior Frontend Engineer @ Brandwatch

( Apr 2013 – Nov 2013

Developed their main product line: brand Analytics

• Wrote codemods to refactor thousands of files, defining conventions for all frontend, reducing code review length and improving time to merge

## Senior Frontend Engineer → Frontend Team Lead @ Content Fleet

**U** Apr 2012 – Mar 2013

- Developed REST APIs and core MVC applications during the startups growth phase
- Led mobile responsiveness efforts and performance optimization initiatives, significantly reducing network calls and minimizing source code for a faster UX, especially on mobile devices
- Responsible for the frontend strategy, conventions, quality, performance improvements and training new team members

# Full-stack Engineer @ Goiás State Government

(S) Fey 2007 – Mar 2012

- · Maintained the State's payroll and other Human Capital Management (HCM) systems for over 200k employees and citizens
- Led several performance, usability and accessibility improvements

#### 🔟 Junior Full-stack Engineer @ DR Sistemas & Interagi

**U** 2004 – 2005

- Interagi: developed CRUD applications and did some programmatic image processing
- DR Sistemas: developed a Backend application for the public law sector

# Misc Software Engineering & Consultancy gigs @ Freelancer

( Jan 2003 – Dec 2014

- Vega Sistemas, Brazil: High-level architecture on migrating a desktop application to a web platform
- SENAC Goiás, Brazil: Consultancy on web development best practices, productivity tools, agile methodologies and programming languages for their internal development department
- Federal University of Goiás, Brazil: Developed their public admission (Vestibular) system and website

#### Other

Over 23 experiences as an instructor or speaker and 7 volunteer positions around leadership, web development, community and the arts. See all of them at luiz.dev/cv/verbose.

## **Education**

#### Degrees

- **▲** Languages
- Business Process Management, MBA @ IT Management Institute (IGTI) Brazil
- Computer Engineering, Bachelor @ Federal University of Goiás Brazil
- Computer Science, Visiting Student @ Saint Mary's University Canada

- Portuguese Native
- English Fluent
- German & Spanish Basic

#### Other

Over 32 courses and specializations taken, 70 books read, 30 events attended and 8 achievements on software engineering, entrepreneurship, leadership and self growth. See all of them at luiz.dev/cv/verbose.

# **Skills and Competencies**

